What the job market
looks like today
versus what it's going to look
like and four years, when folks
graduate, it's constantly
evolving, constantly changing.
Today most people
graduating are going
to have many jobs
throughout their lives.
And so I think success is much
less about having the content
knowledge or
certainly, of course,
there's always some
technical skills you need,
but it's really
about the ability
to be flexible and adapt and
to come into a new workplace
and how have the
confidence and the ability
to get up to speed quickly,
to work well with a team,
to apply some basic
toolset of sort
of quantitative and
qualitative analysis
to many different
topics and issues,
regardless of where you end up.
The thing from my
graduate school education
that was the most
valuable was we
had to do a semester
long group project.
And that very closely mimicked
what my day to day life
was like working
for this consulting
firm for the last nine years.
You had people with very
different work styles.
It's very easy to think that
everybody works the same way
that you do, that everyone
thinks the same way that you
do, that everyone communicates
the same way that you do.
But that's not true
obviously, and learning
how to work with people
who think and work
and communicate differently
than you is undeniably
one of the most important keys
to success in the workplace
today, no matter
what field you're in.
And the group projects force
you to learn how to do that.
In my field, collaboration
is really essential
because every article I
work on involves a writer.
Sometimes the writer has
a research assistant,
and I'm there as an editor.
I have a top editor who looks
at it after I do sometimes two
of them.
We have design people,
we have copy editors,
we have fact checkers,
and everyone's
going to change the
piece a little bit,
including the designers.
Sometimes the designers
will find a piece of art
or do a portrait that makes
me want the story to have
an element it didn't have
before just because of what
they did visually.
So I think the key
thing to realize
is that the end
result is never going
to be exactly what any
one of those people
would have done if they'd been
sitting in a room by themselves
and that that's often
the goal is that it's
better than what the
person would come up
with by themselves.
But even if there
are ways where you
feel a little pinch as a writer,
as an editor, that you didn't
exactly get what you
wanted, but there's
something really beautiful about
the collective energy of it
that kind of supersedes that.
We all have the ability.
If I wanted to go self-publish
a book, I could do that.
I don't know how
well it would sell.
I think, more often
than not, that dialectic
of going back and forth
with a thesis, antithesis,
synthesis-- so I have an idea,
my boss has a different idea,
we have a phone
conversation, and I say, aha,
I get what you're saying here.
Let's do the third thing.
It sharpens it and sharpens
it and sharpens it,
and that's why we have editors.
That's the reason for it.
People also have
layers of distance
from the piece that
give them perspective
that you wouldn't have if you've
been living and breathing it
night and day.
So in the end I think, just
as in a lot of areas in life,
it's a constant conversation
between what we could control
and what we can't
control, and then
what comes out of that is life.
People who are
strategic thinkers
don't just accept what
they're told necessarily.
I think all of our fields
are constantly evolving,
and the way that we're taught
how to do things or the way
that we're taught that
the world is evolves.
And so in our
work, it was really
important to have people
who would regularly
question those things and bring
new and different perspectives
to the conversation.
Every project that
we did was different.
We did not follow a
template in our work.
So we had hundreds of
clients over the years,
and each time we sat
down with the client,
and we understood their problem,
and we designed a process that
was going to help them
get to the solution
that they were looking for,
that was unique to that client.
Because the context
of the culture
and the politics
and the people is
different in every situation.
And so folks who would not be
considered strategic thinkers
would just say, OK well
how did we do that before?
Let's just apply that
same thing over again.
But what we were really
trying to get to was like,
OK, it's important to
think about what worked
and what didn't work about how
we've done things in the past,
and then adapt that to meet the
unique needs of this situation.
And I think that
is a skill, again,
that is essential probably no
matter what field you're in,
because again, the world
is evolving so quickly.
We can't just accept
the way that things
have been done in the past.
In my field, and I think in a
lot of fields, what people are
looking for is the ability
to see the big picture
and focus really
sharply on details.
And sometimes people are too
much of one or the other.
They have good big
picture thinking
but they can't zero in.
Or sometimes they're
very detail oriented,
but they lose sight
of the big picture.
So I think part of
what I was referring
to when I talked about
agility is that ability
to go back and forth between
seeing the big topic,
and then focusing in on
all the different areas.
And so when we get cover
letters, and we get resumes,
we're looking for
specific skills.
I work at a magazine that
focuses on science and history
mostly, so we're looking to
see like, oh, interesting,
they have a minor in history.
Or look at that, they
also study physics.
So we're looking for areas where
they could be helpful to us.
But we're also
looking at curiosity,
as one of the students put it.
That's just whether they
have the kind of mind
that just wants to learn
and uncover things.
That's such an important
skill for so many jobs,
and certainly my line of work.