I think the only thing that
helped me make difficult
decisions was continuing to
be put in difficult situations
It's realizing, OK, I really
don't like my life right now,
I'm really unhappy.
No one is going to
change it for me but me.
So I need to either get
up and do something,
or I'm going to stay like
this for the rest of my life.
And it's doing that
time and time again,
that's the only thing
that makes it easier.
It's just, you've got
to keep getting up.
You can't just stay miserable.
After my first semester
stage managing,
I did realize that it was
a thing that I enjoyed
and that I really did--
I did like being in
charge or the person that
organizes everything and
make sure that things happen.
And I like being
in control, so it
was a very fitting role
for me, because I like
to think I'm fairly good at it.
So it just worked.
It was just like,
I'm already organized
and I'm already
on top of things.
So it just came naturally.
It really didn't take
any effort for me
to become a stage manager.
It was just like all natural
traits that I already had,
and they just flourished.
And that's when I realized,
Oh, hey, I have these traits.
Yeah, I thought I did, but
like no, you actually do,
because you're doing it.
And now people are telling
you you're doing it well.
So you actually do
have the traits.
You're using them well.
So that was when I realized--
I think that was
actually a really big
self-identifying
point in my life too.
Because it did make me realize,
you're capable of a lot.
If you can take a semester's
worth of engineering classes
and also keep track of
college student actors,
Yeah, I think you're
doing all right.
Even though difficult
things happen,
and things get uncomfortable,
and you're not sure what to do.
When you become uncertain,
or you become scared,
or you become just a mess
maybe, in some cases.
It's just a matter
of doing it anyways.
It doesn't matter
if you're scared,
it doesn't matter if you have
doubts, you have to just do it.
Go for it.
Because if you don't,
then you'll never know.
You can't let fear stop you.
Every day, fear has the
opportunity to stop you,
but you just have to keep going.
You have to do things scared.
Doesn't matter if you're
scared or not, just do it.
Just do it.
Well, I think for those
of us, many of us who
have lost years in our 20s,
they can be a little scary
while we're in them.
But then we look back later
and we're so grateful for them.
And I think one
thing that's valuable
is to think of what made
them orienting years?
As you said, what
made them years
where we actually learn
something about ourselves
and got on to a better path?
Because I certainly
have friends who
maybe did that for a little
too long and then got
into their late
30s and early 40s
and still hadn't caught the
train they're waiting for.
| think one thing is
limiting those years.
So if you spend a
year doing something,
and you've gained something
but it's not really the track
you want to be on, that's fine.
But you don't want to make
it 5 or 10 years of that.
So that's one
principle I would say.
Another principle is,
once it's been six months
or you're stopping
and I'm thinking, OK,
what have I gained from this?
What have I learned from this?
And if I don't want to
continue in this direction,
how can I build on those skills
and those things that I enjoy?
For me, for example, I
taught school for a year.
And I didn't want to be a
school teacher in the end,
but I really enjoyed helping
the students edit their papers
and come up with ideas.
And they realized that I
wanted to be an editor, got me
that much closer to what I did.
Ultimately, end up doing it.
And working with people
it was really delightful.
So I think that's
really valuable.
I think it's just like, I don't
know a lot about agriculture,
but my understanding
is that it helps
to let the fields go
fallow every so often,
or to plant different crops
to rotate crops through.
And I think it's
the same with life.
I think even when you've been
in your career for a while,
it helps to bring in
some fresh energy.
So if you can really
harvest that in those years.
Say, you spend a
year and go to Europe
and do something different.
If you're harvesting
fresh energy
that you can then
bring back, that
makes that not
actually a lost year.
It makes it a found year.
And much more fruitful
than if you just
kept your nose to the grindstone
and stayed in the same line
you'd been in.
So my undergraduate
education really
did focus on all
different disciplines.
The first year program
really made sure
that students had a handle
on the basics of art,
and electronic
engineering, and physics.
And for me, that really
helped me think broadly.
I'm a journalist
and I'm an editor,
so actually in a
very literal sense,
these are all areas
I touch on here
and there throughout my work.
But I think even in
more narrow fields,
you think about great thinkers
like Einstein, for example,
and how he played the violin.
Or you hear stories
about Nikola Tesla,
and I remember hearing in my
electronic engineering class
that he was on a walk reciting
poetry when he suddenly
had a vision for
something that would
become his main breakthrough
for engineering.
And I think, when you get too
stuck in one rut of thinking,
you don't have those creative
outside the box ideas.
And so I think
general education is
really important for
teaching your brain
to function in all different
ways that can wake you up
when you least expect it.