I think the other thing
that I would recommend
is, again, based on what I
didn't do but in retrospect
I wish I had, which
was to take more intro
classes in different
subjects, and to explore
different potential
career pathways.
I came into college as an
environmental studies major,
and it worked out well for me.
It worked out great for
me, and I loved what I did.
But I didn't even consider
that there were other things
out there, and I wish I would
have taken intro to psychology,
and some sort of intro to law,
or some more science classes.
But for taking
those intro classes,
how do you know if that's
something that's really
going to spark your interest?
So I would really
recommend using
those four years to explore
different career pathways.
Because again, it's
not going to be
a waste if you take an
intro to psych class
and you don't like it.
You are still going to get
valuable tools and skills
from that, undoubtedly.
I don't know if I've
mentioned this before,
but I remember when I was
in college studying science,
but we were required
to also take
certain classes like
the counseling, that
is, introduction to counseling.
And then I was told to study
educational psychology,
and then philosophy.
We also had to take that.
In fact, those days, us as
science students had questions
like, what do I
need philosophy for?
What do I need counseling for?
That's not what I'm going to do.
But now, looking back, even
though I thought they were not
helpful, looking
back-- in fact, I
will say that I'm
actually relying heavily
on some of these classes that
I thought were not useful.
One major regret
that I had was, when
I was in high school my music
teacher had always said,
Solomon, you had a very
excellent music integration.
We used to laugh at each other.
People would laugh at me
because I was studying music,
and so I stopped.
And I regret up to now.
Because if I had done it,
even as part of my business,
I would have used it a lot in
my current counseling practice.
But if I had done it, even
when I came to America,
it would have been easier for
me because the church I went to,
they needed someone to
play the keyboard for them.
And I was so good at it,
I just loved everything.
So as a young student
in the colleges,
I will encourage all of them, I
would just encourage them that,
give yourself that opportunity.
Be open.
As I said earlier, be
fluid in you're learning,
and then study other
areas that you might think
that you have no interest.
And at the end of the day, it
would be very useful to you.
That is one thing
I will recommend
or I would suggest
to college students.
Explore everything, do
everything, try everything.
Even if you're scared to
try it, try it anyways.
Even if you don't think
you're going to be good at it,
do it anyways.
Even if you think it's probably
going to not be so fun,
give it a shot anyways.
You're not losing
anything, you're not
missing out on anything,
you're just giving things a try
Why do you think that giving
it a try is important?
Because if you don't
try, you'll never
know what could have been.
You just have to try.
That's the first step.
That's literally the
first step, is to try.
Without trying,
there's no motion.
I think a career is a quest.
I think life is a quest.
And a career ends up being
a very important part
of how you spend
your time and energy
and what you
contribute to the world
and what you gain
from the world.
I do think, though,
that there are so
many different
things you could do,
so you should
never feel that you
have one chance to get that
gold goblet or whatever it is.
As if the end of
the quest, the pot
of gold at the end
of the rainbow.
There are a lot of
rainbows and a lot
of directions you could go.
But since time is limited,
certain point once you've
looked around a
bit and explored,
you want to start thinking
one step in front of the other
and leading yourself
towards somewhere.
And I would just say,
never feel limited,
always look for clues that
show you what you enjoy.
Build relationships.
Make sure that you're listening
to people as well as speaking.
And ask lots of
questions, people
love being asked questions.
Makes them feel special like
they actually know something.
So never hesitate to reach out
to someone even if it seems
like a long shot just
to come to their office
and talk to them even if
there's not a job available.
And just be a person
who is excited to be
part of something.
Who's excited to
be part of a team,
who's curious about everything.
And I think if you
approach life that way,
you'll find what
you're looking for.